Guide to the Hans W. Loewald Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hans W. Loewald papers
1910-1999
MS 1721
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.75
The papers include correspondence, writings, and notes, which document Hans Loewald's influence in the fields of psychiatry and psychoanalysis as a writer, teacher, and clinician.
Loewald, Hans W., 1906-1993
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Elizabeth L. Loewald, 1997, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Dr. Hans L. Holocaust testimony (HVT-205) [videotape]. Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimony, Yale University Library.
Biographical / Historical
Hans W. Loewald was born in 1906 in the Alsatian town of Colmar. After serving a medical internship in Berlin, Loewald left his native Germany. He received his medical degree from the University of Rome in 1934 and practiced psychiatry in Padua until 1939, after which he moved to the United States. There, he was an assistant professor in psychiatry at the University of Maryland Medical School and, from 1955 through 1974, was an active member of the Yale University School of Medicine faculty in psychiatry. He affiliated with the Western New England Institute for Psychoanalysis in 1955 and served as its president. Loewald died on January 9, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The papers include correspondence, writings, and notes, which document Hans Loewald's influence in the fields of psychiatry and psychoanalysis as a writer, teacher, and clinician.
Psychiatry; Psychoanalysis; Loewald, Hans W., 1906-1993; Western New England Institute for Psychoanalysis
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The papers are composed primarily of correspondence and writings, which document Hans Loewald's career in psychiatry. The papers do not include personal materials documenting his early training or his decision to emigrate and, except for a few photographs, date largely from his time in the United States. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically, while writings with known dates are chronologically arranged. Undated writings follow, arranged alphabetically by title. For both published or unpublished writings, the files may include notes, drafts, and associated correspondence.
  - Bibliographies, résumés, memoirs, writings about Loewald, 1950-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1948-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    - Fogel, Gerald, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Greenberg, Daniel, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Houston-Galveston Psychoanalytic Society, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Meninger Foundation [Topeka Conference], 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pious, William L., 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Robert P. Knight Fund [research project], 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Rockefeller Foundation [residential program at Bellagio Center], 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Schafer, Roy, 1966-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Western New England Institute for Psychoanalysis
    - Interaction course, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Termination seminar, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings
    - "La cura delle artropatie croniche con iniezioni endorachidiane di fenolsulfonftaleina", 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Osservazioi neurologiche nella cura insulinica", 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Contributo alla misurazione della forma e grandezza della sella tureica nei tumori endo e parasellari", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Disenchantment", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Some Aspects of Modern Psychiatry" [includes Italian translation], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Review of A Holistic Approach to Biology Derived from Pathological Data in Man, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "The Unconscious and Our Culture", 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Freud's Psychoanalytic Theories", 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Discussion: I. Hendrick's 'Early Development of the Ego II' ", 1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Psychoanalysis and Modern Views on Human Existence and Religious Experience", 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Personality and Religion. A Psychoanalytic View" [formerly "Christianity and Modern Man"], 1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Contribution to the Theory of Therapeutic Action and Technique of Psychoanalysis", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "On the Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalysis", 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Transference and the Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalysis", 1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Comments on Some Instinctual Manifestations of Superego Formation", 1961 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "On Internalization", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "On Parricide and the Oedipus Complex", 1965-1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "Activity-Passivity" [American Psychoanalytic Association, fall meeting panel], 1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Review of Wolfgang Lech's Veraussetzungen, Mechanismen und Grenzen des psychoanalytischen Prozesses, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Some Considerations on Repetition and Repetition Compulsion" [includes correspondence with Repetition and Repetition Compulsion Discussion Group], 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - "Psychic Structure and Internalization", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Psychoanalytic Theory and the Psychoanalytic Process", 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "The Experience of Time", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Perspectives on Memory" [Brill Memorial Lecture], 1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - "Panel on Transference", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - "Current Views Toward a Psychoanalytic Concept of Object Relations", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "New Horizons in Metapsychology" [introduction to a panel], 1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "Primary and Secondary Process and Language" [Freud Anniversary Lecture, Psychoanalytic Association of New York], 1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Transference and Countertransference: the Root of Psychoanalysis", 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Review of The Selected Papers of Margaret S. Mahler, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Regression: Some General Considerations" [with discussion by Kenneth T. Calder], 1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Papers on Psychoanalysis, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - "Qualifications of the Psychoanalyst", 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - "Sublimation: An Inquiry" [Freud Lecture of the New York Psychoanalytic Institute], 1981, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - "Zur Frage der Sublimierung", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "Comments on the Psychoanalytic Concept of Symbolism" [Hartman Award Lecture], 1983 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - "Le Transfert et la Contre-Transfert", 1984 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - "Transference-Countertransference", 1984, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - "Religious and Moral Dimensions of Psychoanalysis", 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "Some Theoretical Considerations on the Development of Psychic Structure" [panel at meeting of the American Psychoanalytic Association, comments], 1986 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - "On the Mode of Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalytic Psychotherapy, or How Does Treatment Help?", 1986 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - "An Investigation of Religious and Moral Implications of Psychoanalytic Theory and Therapy", 1987 (Box 3, Folder 56-58)
    - Sublimation: A Psychoanalytic Inquiry, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
    - "Termination Analyzable and Unanalyzable", 1988 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "Sublimation, Symbolization and Mourning" [Hartman Lecture], 1980s (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Book [untitled, drafts], undated (Box 3, Folder 63-65)
    - "Case of Psychogenic Asthma", undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - "The Concept of Defense", undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - "Concepts of Reality", undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "Essay on Psychoanalytic Technique", undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - "Initial Stages in the Treatment of a Case of Schizophrenia", undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - "Instinct Theory, Object Relations, and Psychic Structure Formation", undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - "Internalization and Defense", undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - "Interpretation, Personal Motivation, Instinct", undated (Box 4, Folder 73-76)
    - "On the Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalysis", undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - "Psychoanalysis in Search of Nature", undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - "Remarks on Psychoanalytic Theory and Psychoanalytic Technique", undated (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - "Stanley Leavy: The Theme and the Word, Further Reflections on Jacques Lacan", undated (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - "Termination, Analyzable and Unanalyzable", undated (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - "Theoretical and Technical Considerations Regarding Variations in Psychoanalytic Technique", undated (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - "Transference and the Therapeutic Action of Psychoanalysis", undated (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - "Transformazione", undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - "The Unconscious", undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - Fragments and notes, 1953, 1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 86-88)
  - Photographs, 1910-1986 (Box 4, Folder 89)